# estefanía mejía

Bio-designer and Interactive Designer specialized in Material R&D. My work explores the intersection of design, materiality, emerging technologies, and digital fabrication.

With over 10 years of experience, I have led multidisciplinary teams in creative projects at various scales. My career has evolved from digital design and creative direction to the exploration of biomaterials, e-textiles, experimental 3D printing, and biocomposites applied across multiple industries.

I am passionate about academia, **research**, **and creative exploration**. I have worked as a sessional lecturer, research assistant, and project consultant. My interdisciplinary approach allows me to connect creativity, technology, and materiality to generate new opportunities for application and experimentation. Currently based in Barcelona.

estefaniamejia.com

estefania.mejia.q@gmail.com

in/estefaniamejiaq

+34 641 684 511

# Work experience

# MATERIAL R&D SPECIALIST / MATERIAL LAB & BIOLAB LEAD

Roth Architecture · MEXICO · APR. 2022 - MAY. 2024

Material Specialist for the R&D team. Innovation and Development Leader for the Materials and BioLab Laboratory of Azulik Group, driving experimentation with bio-plastics, alternative cementing compounds, and novel natural materials in architecture, such as salt. A catalyst for exploration and co-creation with living organisms such as fungi and bacteria, promoting the integration of emerging biomaterials into innovative construction systems.

#### **INNOVATION & DEVELOPMENT**

Lowpoly · SPAIN · SEP. 2020 - MAY. 2021

Digital designer and researcher, specialized in digital fabrication and 3D printing projects. Expert in sustainable materials, biomaterials research, and circular economy processes. Creativity and brand development strategies.

## **DESIGNER. BIOMATERIALS & SOFT ELECTRONICS EXPERT**

Freelance · HYBRID · 2012 - 2024

Designer, educator, and workshop leader in biomaterials research and development. Consultant for material implementation in immersive spaces for various groups, academic institutions, and brands. Development of communication and design strategies for independent interaction projects.

# **DIRECTOR OF STRATEGY & EXPERIMENTATION IN NEW TECHNOLOGIES**

Absurdo Studio · COLOMBIA · JAN. 2018 - SEP. 2019

Digital design communication strategist for clients at Absurdo Studio. Co-direction at the experimentation lab, Absurdo Lab. Leader of research, development, and creative exploration of projects focused on new materials and interaction with emerging technologies.

## SESSIONAL LECTURER / RESEARCH ASSISTANT

ICESI University · COLOMBIA · AUG. 2018 - SEP. 2019

Design, communication, and textile technology sessional lecturer at the Department of Humanities and Social Sciences, ICESI University. Research assistant for seminars on Art and Pedagogy, Sociology of Design, and Textile Research and Creation.

## Advanced skills

Biomaterials, Biotextiles, Experimental 3D printing, Biofabrication, Programming (Arduino/Processing), Electronics, e-textiles.

#### **Education**

FASHION FUTURES: NEW MATERIALS AND WEARABLE TECHNOLOGY

Maeten

Istituto Europeo di Design • 2020 • Spain

HIGHER EDUCATION TEACHING Professional certificate

ICESI University • 2018 • Colombia

INTERACTIVE MEDIA DESIGN University Degree

ICESI University • 2012 • Colombia

**DIGITAL MARKETING - Course**Hyper Island • 2016 • Sweden (online)

STRATEGIC PLANNING - Course
Academ UGAP • 2015 • Guatemala

ACADEMIC ENGLISH - Course University of Sheffield • 2012 • UK

## Work experience

#### REGIONAL DIGITAL ACCOUNT DIRECTOR

4am Saatchi & Saatchi / Hashtag Labs · GUATEMALA · SEP. 2016 - JUL. 2017

Direction, supervision and strategic development of digital creative projects, including social media, web, and apps for companies in Guatemala and Central America, including Domino's & Gatorade.

## **DIGITAL CREATIVE PROJECT COORDINATOR**

Starcom Mediavest · GUATEMALA · JUN. 2015 - SEP. 2016

Creative coordination and project supervision in web development, social media strategy, and UX design consulting for major brands, including Walmart Central America and its regional supermarket chains

#### **DIGITAL PROJECT MANAGER**

Leo Burnett • GUATEMALA • JUN. 2013 - JUN. 2015

Coordination and project supervision for interactive, multimedia, web, and social media projects for brands in Guatemala and Central America, including Procter & Gamble. UX/UI consultancy and interactive leadership for digital innovation projects.

#### Awards & exhibitions

MAWRID: CELEBRATING INSPIRED DESIGN • Exhibition

Design Space Alula

IRTH بث • Exhibition

18th International Architecture Exhibition La Biennale di Venezia - National Pavilion of Saudi Arabia

2023 • ITALY

# SPECIAL MASTER SCHOLARSHIP • Scholarship

Istituto Europeo di Design

2019 · SPAIN

## ACADEMIC EXCELLENCE SCHOLARSHIP • Scholarship

ICESI University

2007-2012 · COLOMBIA

#### **HONOR ROLL** • Award

**ICESI University** 

2009 - 2011 · COLOMBIA

# Complementary skills

Product design, Research, Development, Teaching, Project direction, Team leading, SCRUM, Conceptualization, Strategy, Communication.

# Languages

Spanish, English & una miqueta de Català;)

